This video is all about one of my
Patreon supporters called Clive. He's
having a really tough time at the
moment. And even through all that, he
just wanted some good ice cream. But
he's also [music]
diabetic. So for you, Clive, today is
Clive's luxury chocolate hazelnut
gelatte.
Diabetics, you got to watch the sugars.
So that means carbs. We have to also
watch the lactose which lactose is just
a type of sugar um in a roundabout kind
of way. So to make this luxury we do
have to use some dairy but I've
substituted the milk for cashew milk. So
we're going to use alilos and stevia
because he is North America. Uh I will
put a xylitol version in the
description. it's not going to be as
good because you can't use anywhere near
as much xylitol as you can alos and that
affects the solids content. But I do
want to just point out one thing. Inulin
has been the substitute for skim milk
powder for plant-based recipes for ages
now. There is a new ingredient that we
can use but I just can't get it here and
that is citrus fiber and it looks like
this.
It is excellent. I was able to get a
very small amount enough to try and when
it becomes available, I'm going to start
using that. So, if that's something that
you like to make, you like to convert my
recipes into plant-based, I recommend if
you can get it, you get the citrus fiber
instead of inulin. That said, let's make
this gelato something super special. For
Clive's luxury chocolate hazelnut
gelato, you are going to need 540 gram
of unsweetened cashew milk, 200 gram of
cream, between 30 and 36% fat, 160 g of
alulose, 50 g of inulin, 75 g of cocoa
powder, so that's unsweetened cocoa
powder. It's not drinking chocolate,
that's cocoa powder. 1 gram of salt,
between four and five grams of
stabilizer, and then one gram of stevia
liquid. That's what we're going to use.
The stevia is to boost sweetness cuz we
don't get that higher sweetness level
from the alulose. And the cashew milk
also dulls that sweetness level down.
So, with that in mind, let's get
everything out and weighed up. Right,
let's start with our cashew milk. So,
this any any brand is fine. Just check
the sugars. We don't want the added
sugars. 540 g into that 200 g of our
cream minus 33%.
Into that 1 g of salt into that 75 g of
cocoa powder. Make this a good one.
Strong cocoa powder. So this is extra
brute. You can just use cacao berry
brute. Just whatever cocoa powder you
like. Just make sure that it's a really
nice strong flavor profile and not a
milk chocolate weak profile. So 75 g
alulos we're going to weigh out with our
inulin.
160 g of alulos
into our alulos. I'm going to add a
stabilizer. I'm going to do a video next
week on what is in here. This is my mix.
I've done videos on this before but my
mix changes. So into that we're going to
add 4 and 12 to 5 gram of stabilizer
because this is gelato. So it's much
lower fat relatively speaking um to US
ice cream. And because of that and
because we're not using huge amount of
cream, we don't have the milk solids
non-fat in this as well. So we need that
stabilizer to help bring the texture
where we want it. That can go in our
pan. And then finally, our inulin. This
is well within
the safe range. Uh, unless you eat, you
know, a kilo of this stuff in one go,
then you'll be fighting for a week. But,
um, who's going to do that? 50 grams of
inulin. That is everything apart from
our stevia. We are not going to cook the
stevia. It can make a potentially
already bitter product, even more
bitter. So, we're going to put this in
after we've cooked it. Again, my
stabilizer is a heated stabilizer, so we
need to make sure we bring that up to 80
to 85C for a couple of minutes to make
sure everything is cooked off. And I've
just realized that I didn't record me
putting any of the ingredients in the
pan. So, you're going to have to I will
flash up on the screen what they are.
But here we go. Stir, stir. On the heat.
This goes 80 to 85C for 2 or 3 minutes.
Right. There we go. There is our
base cooked off, ready to go. Looks
delicious.
Smells delicious. Let's get this our
container.
Nice. And finally, we have stevia. There
are different types of stevia. Uh some
are more bitter than others, but we are
literally just putting
one gram in there. And that is
to boost the perceived sweetness of this
in line with normal sugared ice creams.
That can now go in the fridge overnight.
Please. This needs time for those
flavors to develop. So, let's pop that
in the fridge. If you want to chill this
down in an ice bath, then by all means,
go ahead and do that. And then you churn
it right away. But I would like those
flavors to develop more. So, I am going
to chill it overnight. Whilst that is
chilling, if you don't have these final
two ingredients, you might want to pop
out and get these hazelnuts. You can get
these from Bog Bun or any supermarket in
the UK, but these came from Amazon, I
think, because Bog Bum are out near me.
Uh, these are unsweetened. Raw is fine
or roasted, but um I'm going to roast
these a little bit more. And some
chocolate. Now, obviously, chocolate by
and large, if you buy something like
coovvere chocolate, then the dark
chocolates don't have sugar above a
certain percentage. If you go to the
store, even lint, and you look at
something that's 90, 85%, 95%, it will
have added sugar in it. So, it's much
safer to go for 100%
chocolate. Now, this is going to be
super strong. So, we're not going to eat
this from the bar. We're going to shave
this finally in our gelato when it's
churning. So, pop out and get these if
you don't have them. This one's going to
be a really good one. Yes, it is 7:45
[music]
in the morning. My wife has taken my kid
to school and I'm making ice cream. Why
[music] not? So, out the fridge. Give it
a good mix. Make sure it's all
completely combined for putting it into
our pre-chilled ice cream machine. Make
sure it comes [music] up to just above
the bottom of that top dasher there.
That's a perfect kind of place. Let's
get that spinning. Look how gorgeous
that is. Anyway, I've toasted these
hazelnuts for another 10 minutes at
about 250 fah, something like [music]
that. And I'm just going to remove any
skins that will come off. This is our
chocolate. Whilst those nuts cool down,
fancy looking chocolate. Look, I'm going
to chop this chocolate up because I want
it nice and [music] small. I did try
grating this in, but the grater was
junk. So, with it nearly at the end of
the churn, in goes our chocolate. There
is approximately 50 g of chocolate in
this 1 kilo base. The nuts have cooled
down now. Chopping them up and putting
them in right at the end. The smell is
delicious. Now it's time to load up our
containers. [music]
There's a good amount in here. We got
about 1.3
lers [music] worth of ice cream out of
this mix, which means we got 30%
overrun. Perfect for gelato. [music]
Let's go.
Clives chocolate hazelnut
diabetic friendly gelato. This scooped
perfectly as you can see from this clip.
It looks incredible. Great texture. Just
watch how much of that 100% chocolate
you put in. It's super bitter stuff. So,
we don't want to overpower any flavors.
We just want to put a little bit in just
to create, you know, another level. So,
we've got that delicious ice cream,
those roasted hazelnuts, and that
chocolate. Let's dive in and see how we
did on this one.
Oh, that's so good.
Perfect texture throughout.
Diabetic ice cream doesn't have to be
bad. This is amazing ice cream
regardless of whether it's diabetic
friendly or not. If you bought this, if
you're a chocolate ice cream fan, you
bought this in a scoop shop, you would
be super, super pleased. So, give this
one a try. Those hazelnuts,
these ones are actually dry roasted, but
I did roast them, as I showed you, a
little bit longer just to boost that
flavor. I find them a little bit weak
sometimes when you buy pre-roasted nuts.
So, get your nuts in the oven and boost
them up a bit more. Watch the chocolate
that you put into this as an addin. Like
I said before, we want to use that 100%
chocolate because we don't want to add
any more sugar into our recipe. We've
got to keep that sugar count down. We've
also got to look at our lactose
inclusion in our ice creams for
diabetics. That's kind of what we need
to keep in check with diabetic friendly
ice creams. Hope you enjoyed this video.
Don't forget to like and subscribe. Got
two other channels. I've got the
Chocolate Ears Kitchen, which is this
one, where every week or two weeks,
depending on how busy I am, I make bon
bonss, luxury desserts, real pro kind of
stuff. And if you're a nerd like me,
then I also have a 3D printing channel
where I make lots of pop culture
referenced stuff from movies, games, and
TV shows. And that is this channel here.
So head over, subscribe, like, do all
that kind of stuff if that's your thing.
Thanks very much for watching. Don't
forget to like and subscribe to this
channel and I will see you next week
when I've got a Japanese ingredient up
in a cupboard that I've been wanting to
use for a while. So we're going to do a
Japanese ice cream and talk about
stabilizers a little bit more.